Hey,
Speaker 1 (lower-pitched voice): everybody. So yesterday, May 14th, I had the
Speaker 2 (lower-pitched voice): privilege of speaking to Mike Gravel, who
served in
Speaker 2 (lower-pitched voice): the Senate from Alaska from 1969 to 1981. He ran for president in 2008 in the Democratic primaries, appeared in the debates that cycle, and had a number of notable exchanges with the candidates, including Hillary Obama and Biden,
and
And he
Speaker 2 (lower-pitched voice): is now running again for president at the age of 89, after having been recruited to do so by some teens in New York, which
is a
Speaker 2 (lower-pitched voice): very quirky and amusing, actually encouraging story. And we get into some of that in our interview, as well as a variety of other issues. So I hope you'll enjoy it.
All right, Senator Mike Revell,
Speaker 2 (lower-pitched voice): thank you so much for doing this. Well, thank you for having me
Speaker 3: on your program.
so I
Speaker 5 (lower-pitched voice): like many first became acquainted with you in 2007 2008 when you appeared in those Democratic primary debates and you definitely had a substantially different message than most of the candidates I'm
Speaker 1 (lower-pitched voice): sort of curious to hear you reflect back on what you perceive as the impact of your presence in those debates and in that race in 2008
Speaker 6 (lower-pitched voice): more broadly
Man 7: Well, I don't think I had that much of an impact. I think Obama came in and sucked up all the oxygen and overwhelmingly won, and unfortunately he didn't accomplish anything other than getting a black man elected. But what's happened is that all of the video, I was in seven debates, all of the videos and
the debates.
Man 7: registered but not sufficient from a campaign point of view
and now
Man 7: what's happened is my celebrity or notoriety whatever you want to call it is energized by all those debate points made in 07-08 are now fueling
Man 7: the present possibility of a debate, or my involvement in the debate, assuming we can make it to 65,000 votes. So, the effect, it's interesting, I think you have to conclude that I was ahead of my time in '08, and it seems that the message that I have then is very germane to the present.
Speaker 6 (lower-pitched voice): Right, and you now have a
Speaker 1 (lower-pitched voice): group of young people who are running your social media accounts and so forth How do you assess their performance so far? Well, very
Man 7: good And of course it was a big surprise to me because when David Oaks called me and said when I run for president I pointed out
Speaker 8 (lower-pitched voice): to him. Do you have any idea how old I am? Well, I'm 89 years
old and
Speaker 8 (lower-pitched voice): and so I'll be 90 next year
Man 7: when the convention takes place, but what the point he made, and I think it's valid, is that it's the issues that count, not necessarily the personalities or the age or participation of the individuals. And so the other thing that they used to persuade me was that
Man 7: They had a bevy of positions and issues that I ascribed to, but the one that they had at the top of the list, because they had done research as to what floats by boat, that was the creation of the legislature of the people. And that's what I think is the most important contribution I can make to these debates is that the likelihood, and of course I'm very supportive of Bernie Sanders, Kelsey Gabbard,
Man 7: and Elizabeth Warren. And so, but the likelihood after they get elected to these high offices of their being able to enact their agenda is somewhat limited, because if you look at the dynamics of the Senate, I think we'll get control of the Senate, but not with 60 votes to spare. And that means that a minority of Republicans
Man 7: who as a group are crazy as all get out, they would be able to sabotage and support any of the advances we would hope to make with the agenda items that Bernie and Tulsi and Warren talk about. So that leads to the question,
Man 7: How can we get this progressive agenda enacted? In my mind, the only way we can do it is to empower the people to make laws by creating a legislature of the people whereby people can turn around and enact policies in partnership with their elected officials. Now, the elected officials presently have a monopoly on lawmaking.
Man 7: And that's what we have to change and I'm just completing a book, it'll be out in mid-summer, which essentially is a manual for the implementation of a constitutional amendment and a federal statute, the Legislative Procedures Act, and so with these two legal elements the people would be able
to...
Man 7: enact legislation addressing all of the items that Bernie talks about and Tulsi and the others. So that really, without the legislature of the people, I just really have great fear that we won't be able to get that much enacted that needs to be enacted.
You brought up
Speaker 5 (lower-pitched voice): the issue of age and there's been discussion about
how
Speaker 5 (lower-pitched voice): leading candidates in the Democratic primary field anyway are quite old at least by historical standards I mean it hasn't often been the case that you had people in their upper 70s
you know being seen as
Speaker 5 (lower-pitched voice): the leading contenders for a presidential nomination to what extent do you see scrutiny of that as a legitimate course of action I mean do the voters have a right to try
to
Speaker 5 (lower-pitched voice): assess whether a Joe Biden or a Bernie Sanders has sufficient cognitive capabilities
Speaker 9 (lower-pitched voice): to be able to carry out their duties with sufficient vigor?
I
Man 7: think so. And I think that, look at my age, to be able to...
Man 7: write a book, make myself available for
Speaker 8 (lower-pitched voice): interviews at 89. I would have never thought I'd lived this long, but when I first ran was
Man 7: when I was in my
70s.
And
Man 7: so, no, I think Bernie Sanders acquits himself extremely well. As long as he's healthy, he's good to 95. And so all we need is four years of him, and hopefully within that four years, we can enact the legislature of the people and they'll get his agenda through. Now, I'd like to see him with Tulsi Gabbard as Vice
Speaker 10 (lower-pitched voice): President.
Speaker 10 (lower-pitched voice): She's not quite 39 or she's just 39. She's 38.
She's 38.
Speaker 10 (lower-pitched voice): She's 38. Well then, you know, it wouldn't be a crime to have her serve as vice president for eight years or four years and get
Man 7: additional experience. She has a lot of experience right now, six years on the legislative, six years at the foreign relations committee and six years on the military affairs
Speaker 10 (lower-pitched voice): committee.
Speaker 10 (lower-pitched voice): This, in my mind, equips her to be able to, and she's the only one. Now, Bernie has joined her to a degree, and that is to address the problem, the excesses
of
Man 7: the military-industrial complex. And so, what's real sad is that you don't see any of the, here you've got 20+ candidates, and nobody's really addressing the military-industrial complex other than Tulsi and Bernie.
Man 7: What does that say? They get elected to anything. They'll just be puppets of the military industrial complex. And that's what's wrong with our society right now.
-
Speaker 11: Right, so I'm curious to actually hear you go into a little bit greater depth about what you see as the key differences
Speaker 1 (lower-pitched voice): between Tulsi and Bernie. So famously Tulsi resigned from the DNC in 2016 to endorse Bernie, their personal friends. I've interviewed her at length.
Speaker 1 (lower-pitched voice): before. And it seems to me one of their key differences is that Tulsi is a little bit more forthright in discussing, as you mentioned, the issues associated with the military-industrial complex, foreign military adventurism. Even just yesterday, Tulsi appeared on a very popular podcast with Joe Rogan and said that she would see to it that charges were dropped against Julian Assange.
Speaker 1 (lower-pitched voice): and Edward Snowden and I
Speaker 12 (lower-pitched voice): don't see Bernie really going quite that far so I'm wondering you know what your interpretation is
Speaker 8 (lower-pitched voice): no Bernie is focused on
Man 7: domestic issues and and he's even admitted in fact I realized this when he was running the first time and I contributed to his campaign and he submitted that he hasn't focused a great deal on foreign policy well foreign policy is vital
Man 7: And he claims that now he's paying more attention to that, and that's fine with me, but like I say,
Speaker 10 (lower-pitched voice): if he had Tulsi Gabbard as his vice president, or vice versa, if she had him as her vice president, that would be very, very helpful because he is expert on domestic issues.
Speaker 10 (lower-pitched voice): and has experience in that regard and Tulsi of course has expertise beyond
Man 7: that. So I don't fault Bernie for that, you know a member of Congress can only
Speaker 10 (lower-pitched voice): focus on so much to be effective if you're going to be effective in certain areas but if you want to you can be a broad gauge person covering everything.
I
Speaker 10 (lower-pitched voice): defer a lot on domestic issues, like I'm not making myself expert on single payer healthcare, which is what I believed
in and
Speaker 10 (lower-pitched voice): have from the get-go. There are several other areas. Now I have spent time on economic matters to try and figure out how we can get around the
Man 7: shortcomings of capitalism.
Man 7: But here too, it's a question of so many hours
in a day, and
Man 7: if you're a member of Congress, you've got to appear for the
votes and
Man 7: for your committee work.
And a lot
Man 7: of times that doesn't leave time to broaden out. Now Tulsi has the advantage with her two committee assignments, which in Stanley are very unusual. These are two powerful committees. Generally a member doesn't get that kind
of
Man 7: committee assignments. Now another person that I think is very, very helpful, wonderful on the scene, and that's Alexandria Ocasio-Cortez. -
Speaker 13: Okay, I'm
Speaker 14: very impressed with
Speaker 10 (lower-pitched voice): her. And of course I agree, and I
Man 7: think Bernie has joined her on this Green New Deal. This is just vital.
Man 7: I mean, and in the book I'm pointing out that one of the suicide tracks that we're on is, of course, the environment. Now, the Green New Deal would just set us in motion to provide, not only to address the problem domestically, but to also get back on track internationally, because until we get a commitment internationally on this subject,
Man 7: We're going to have some real problems. Now we, there's no question we are one of the foremost polluters, but the problem of growth that's going on in the world, it has to be addressed. We can have growth in an environmentally sound way. The question is you have to want to do it and so it's all muddied up with these Republicans who just really...
Man 7: our reinventing the wheel
Speaker 15: and that's about it I
Speaker 1 (lower-pitched voice): voted for Bernie in the 2016 primaries have always been transparent about that but I have noted that he's made occasional statements here and there that
raise a
Speaker 1 (lower-pitched voice): little bit of concern you know he's at times seemingly given credence to the more conspiratorial notions of the Trump Russia matter he's
Speaker 1 (lower-pitched voice): commented on Venezuela in a way that a lot of even his supporters objected to. How do you sort of advise
Speaker 16: people who are, you know, otherwise inclined to support him who react negatively? First
Speaker 17 (lower-pitched voice): off, what were his comments on Venezuela? I was not aware of that.
Do you
Speaker 17 (lower-pitched voice): recall? I
Speaker 16: don't have them in front of me, but basically he
was –
I'm
Speaker 16: paraphrasing, but he was saying that Maduro is a dictator and basically should be ousted in some manner. He seemed to be giving at least tacit license to the Trump administration's strategy, although he never has endorsed military intervention.
Speaker 11: But it did cause a lot of people to get upset who are otherwise supporters of his.
Man 7: Well, I think that they are holding too tight a standard. What he said is accurate. Maduro is a bit of a fool and a tyrant, but the answer to Maduro or Venezuela's problem with Maduro is not to be affected by us.
Man 7: because he doesn't believe in intervention, but it should be the people. And really what I would advocate is we don't need to make these sanctions on Venezuela, which we've been doing for over a decade. Here stop the sanctions, because what we're doing is we're the ones that are contributing most to the dysfunction.
Man 7: the Maduro government and so if we stop the sanctions then maybe they could get their act together economically whether it's but but here again if the people want to get rid of Maduro they
could.
Man 7: They have held elections, maybe the elections weren't all that great and democratic. But then again, our elections have the same problem, but all you gotta do is look at what happened in Georgia with Stacey Abrams, you know, she would have won had it not been rank suppression by the Republican organization.
Man 7: So, holding Bernie to a standard on Venezuela that really isn't realistic, the holding of the standard, not his position, I think his position is realistic, Maduro is the problem, but we can't discern whether it's the problem, Maduro has a problem with himself or the fact of what we created and what we've created is the dysfunction
of
Man 7: the government through sanctions and its murderers, because it's reported that over 40,000 kids will die as a result of our sanctions. Now, the whole sanction approach to foreign policy is ridiculous, because what it does is it empowers the tyrants who we claim we're sanctioning, but the effect is on the ordinary citizen and the poor.
Man 7: Because our theory is, well, we sanction the country and though it affects the ordinary and the poor, then what they ought to do is revolt as a result of our sanctions. Now this is bizarre thinking and immoral thinking at best.
Man 7: And so, I would not hold Bernie to that tight a standard. Having served in government and in the military, you know, these issues are very clouded. And many times, there's not an up-and-down answer. But I think with respect to Venezuela, one, we should stop the sanctions. If anything, help their economy get back on its feet. And then if the people
who
Speaker 19: have a desire, they can get rid of them. That's my approach.
Speaker 5 (lower-pitched voice): - Okay, and as far as Russia, I actually do have a statement that Bernie made in 2017. He said, "What hold does Russia have over President Trump?" And he suggested that Trump was carrying out foreign policy at the behest of the Russian government and not serving the interests of the American
Speaker 20 (lower-pitched voice): people. That always seemed like
Speaker 20 (lower-pitched voice): a major stretch to me. If you look at Trump's policy record, there's been a lot of belligerence toward Russia. And it just seemed like Bernie is kind of legitimizing aspects of the Russia
Speaker 21: conspiracy narrative that has been pushed by the democratic establishment.
Well, it is
Speaker 21: the
Speaker 17 (lower-pitched voice): democratic establishment. A lot of times, unless
Man 7: you get a chance to study it,
that you
Man 7: fall into the trap of conventional wisdom of the establishment. I think it's crap.
Man 7: Here, you want to talk about control of elections? When Yeltsin was running for re-election, we not only paid for the entire election, but we sent over our consultants to manage the election in Russia, and of course, this was the period when all the oligarchs were raping.
Man 7: the country of their resources, you know, when you see individuals become
billionaires in
Man 7: a month's time or six months' time, you've got to realize that there's something really bad happening. Well, that was happening in Yeltsin, you know, we made it all possible. So for us to now say,
Man 7: or the Russians are interfering in our elections. It's ridiculous. It's ridiculous. And we do enough damage to our elections that we don't need any foreigners to get involved, but foreigners will. Now that we have the internet and digital communication and digital data, anybody can mess around with any election and any activity economically.
I
Man 7: don't know if you're aware of what happened in 17 about the hacking that nearly brought down the global or American economic network by what was done to
Marish.
Man 7: lines and how that ricocheted into the rest of the economy. So no, we're advancing into a very critical technological area that I don't think is properly addressed by the candidates, but whatever is addressed is best addressed by Bernie, Tulsi, and Warren.
- How do
Speaker 6 (lower-pitched voice): you diagnose why it is
Speaker 6 (lower-pitched voice): That
Speaker 1 (lower-pitched voice): Democrats as well as much of the media have fixated to the expense of most every other issue on this Russian narrative for so long and even now they're on the same track I mean you have Congress issuing these contempt declarations with regard to the Attorney General you have it's always on the top of the agenda or so would seem in Washington what fundamentally is the reason why.
Speaker 1 (lower-pitched voice): this has become such a preoccupation
Man 7: well because it's the it serves the interest of Wall Street and the military industrial complex and they essentially controlled media
Man 7: They control both parties. Make no mistake about it. The Democratic Party has got its hand out over there, and you see that with the support for Biden. Where's Biden's support coming from? Obviously, it's mainstream media, and mainstream media is controlled by Wall Street and the military-industrial complex. So that influence is going to be present in the Democratic Party, and it has been present all along.
Man 7: The question is and of course when we say that the person is a centrist, there's no such thing as a centrist today in the Democratic Party because the party has been moved over to the right, starting with Clinton, Bill Clinton, and it's moved over to the right. So when a person says they're a centrist, they're saying that they're
Man 7: They're on the right, they may not be to the far right as the religious nuts are, but they're between the center and the far right. When what we have to do with the election of Bernie and Tulsi, what we have to do is pull the center back to the middle.
So
Man 7: that when a person says I'm a centrist, he really means he's a centrist. And so we can do that by pulling the party over to the progressive political agenda. And that's the reason why I feel very constrained when I hear Democrats saying, well, we can't go for the whole thing. You know, we have to be centrist. What they're saying is they're compromising
before they
Man 7: even engage in the battle, and this is what happened with Obama with the healthcare situation. They gave up in committee. When Obamacare came out of the House committee, 70 plus percent Americans wanted a single payer and they didn't even include that option in the argument that they made then and still make now. Well, we couldn't have done it.
We
Man 7: could, you know, here, I'll tell you that as far as I'm concerned, Obama's going to fail because he's getting mental diminishment every day when you see him, and so it's going to get worse between the next 18 months, and so what we should do is go for the whole enchilada. I think if we go for a progressive agenda, we will win, and we will win substance if we go for, quote, the right middle ground.
Man 7: That Biden is aspiring, we won't get anything but a replay of
Speaker 23: the Obama administration. You
mentioned
Speaker 12 (lower-pitched voice): before that you're roughly supportive of Elizabeth Warren, and I do agree that many of her
Speaker 1 (lower-pitched voice): economic policies anyway are well considered. And I think she does have a breadth of experience that's unique on those topics. But I did note that she was on the floor of the Senate.
Speaker 1 (lower-pitched voice): around two weeks ago Reading into the congressional record parts of the muller report and it actually brought to mind what you did famously Decades ago in reading into the congressional record the Pentagon papers, but Warren seemed to be putting on a bit of a show because unlike the Pentagon Papers The muller reports is accessible to anybody with an internet connection
Speaker 11: So I'm just not sure what she's going for there
Speaker 8 (lower-pitched voice): well,
first of all
Speaker 8 (lower-pitched voice): Don't hold politicians too narrow a criteria, you know, they need visibility, they recognize they need visibility to hawk their wares, to push and get elected, and so I don't fault politicians for that. I do fault politicians for, let's say, like a, and of course he's very bright, Beto, you know, jumping around
Man 7: like he's got Saint Vitus stands.
Man 7: But what he, you know, he still doesn't address the issues the way Bernie, Tulsi, and Warren address them. And that's the same thing with Buttigieg. What horrified me was his statement that Tulsi,
Speaker 8 (lower-pitched voice): not Tulsi, Chelsea Manning, he didn't understand how she could get pardoned by Obama.
Speaker 8 (lower-pitched voice): from a 35-year sentence, the longest sentence ever meted out against a whistleblower.
And
Speaker 16: not pardoned either. Chelsea Manning was commuted.
Yeah,
Man 7: well, that's
Speaker 8 (lower-pitched voice): right.
Speaker 8 (lower-pitched voice): And so now, and she's out of jail right now because the grand jury, where the judge put her in jail, the grand jury ended and are now convening a new grand jury. And so we would fully expect that she would be probably held in contempt of that. But,
Man 7: you know, for Buttigieg to raise that issue gratuitously just really disturbs
me.
Man 7: You know, he's more raising that issue like he did really guarantees that he's going to be a puppet of the military-industrial complex. God, we've had enough puppets in high office
Speaker 17 (lower-pitched voice): subservient to the military establishment.
Yeah,
Speaker 6 (lower-pitched voice): the phenomenon around Buttigieg is a little curious because, you
Speaker 1 (lower-pitched voice): know, he's the mayor of a relatively small city, South Bend, Indiana.
Speaker 1 (lower-pitched voice): And yet he has gotten a significant bump in the polls where he's now somewhat of a top tier contender and he's plastered on all the prestige magazines and his personal life is celebrated. What do you see as the basic reason why liberals in particular seeming to take such a fondness to him?
Speaker 24 (lower-pitched voice): Well…
Speaker 8 (lower-pitched voice): Probably a little bit like the situation with Obama, you know, the liberals, the fact that he was a black man running for president and was credible in that regard, then, you know, you get your liberal bona fides by supporting something like that, and I think there's elements of that with Buttigieg, because he's gay, there's no question the gay community is delirious,
Speaker 8 (lower-pitched voice): with this advancement and I don't fault that in the slightest. But by the same token, Buttigieg does one thing that's very valuable to the military-industrial complex. He doesn't question that. He
Man 7: doesn't question Wall Street. And so, prior to Biden getting on the scene, it was important for the military-industrial complex
to
Man 7: promote him via their control of the media. So he was sucking up the oxygen that should have gone to more meaningful public servants. And so that's what I attribute it to, that he's not a threat to the military-industrial complex or Wall Street. And he does have a, he's bright, there's no question about that, but he articulates a lot of mush.
Man 7: which I mean, you know, bring us together, we're going to compromise and all of that. God, we see that every election cycle by all politicians running for office who think that, you see, they don't want to get into ish specifics because you can alienate people with specifics as you will, you can gain supporters. But where he, where Buttigieg is as advanced,
Man 7: And of course he's riding a crest of media attention that was engineered by these forces of Wall Street, applying it to the military-industry complex, applying it to mainstream media. But now that Biden is on the scene, he'll suck up his oxygen,
Man 7: And people become a little more credible in examining Buttigieg's positions. Like you know, he's been in the service, but we don't see much of a description by him of the service that he's rendered in the military, and I'm very
Speaker 10 (lower-pitched voice): curious about that. I haven't
Speaker 26 (lower-pitched voice): bothered to do research in that regard, but I think that would be something to look into.
Aside from
Speaker 27: Biden, who we'll
Speaker 9 (lower-pitched voice): discuss individually, who do you see in the field as the most insidious presence right now? I
don't
Speaker 8 (lower-pitched voice): know. I haven't focused on that facet of
it to
Speaker 8 (lower-pitched voice): see who's most. There's just so many in the field that, you know, I'm in the process of finishing up a book on politics.
Speaker 8 (lower-pitched voice): which is going to, in my mind, be very important in addressing the problems and solving them by the people and not by representative government. So I don't think I can answer your question, I just have not paid enough attention on all the candidates to see who's occupying the bottom.
Speaker 5 (lower-pitched voice): Okay. I actually want to ask a little bit about your history. You moved to Alaska in the 60s, not long after it achieved statehood, and you forged a
Speaker 6 (lower-pitched voice): political career there relatively quickly and at a somewhat young age.
So how did
Speaker 6 (lower-pitched voice): that inform your worldview, you know, being in a
Speaker 5 (lower-pitched voice): frontier state? I actually was able to spend some time in Alaska last summer in Juneau, and it was, you know, beautiful, beautiful geographically, obviously.
How
Speaker 28: did that inform the values that you brought to elected office?
Well, I
Speaker 24 (lower-pitched voice): brought my values to Alaska.
Speaker 24 (lower-pitched voice): I became a
Speaker 8 (lower-pitched voice): globalist when I was 16, 17 years old. I read a book by Emery Reeve called "The Anatomy of Peace" and how peace could be attained. And so, when I went to Alaska, I had been working in politics since I was 15 years old, and I went to Alaska when I was in my late 20s. Now, I went to Alaska before it became a state. I knew it was going to become a state.
Speaker 8 (lower-pitched voice): But when I got to Alaska, I ran for the territorial legislature and lost. Then I ran for the city council and that was within 18 months of being in Alaska because I went to Alaska to run for public office and to become a senator or a house member. And so I lost the city council race. Then I ran again and now that we're a state, I was able to run for the state legislature.
Speaker 8 (lower-pitched voice): and was elected in a plurality and then went from my freshman to becoming, getting re-elected with the largest number of votes in Anchorage and parlayed that into becoming Speaker of the House. I went from freshman to Speaker and was motivated to get a lot done because operating on
the
I
Speaker 8 (lower-pitched voice): was ambitious, I wanted to get elected to the higher office, so I got to show accomplishments. And so I did provide unusual leadership at that point in Alaska's development. But in
Man 7: Alaska, I just enjoyed the beauty. I was always suspicious to people because I didn't hunt or fish, but I loved to
Speaker 8 (lower-pitched voice): go walking in the mountains and I did the Choku Trail.
Speaker 8 (lower-pitched voice): We did the trail that surrounded around the backside
Man 7: of the Chugach Mountains of Anchorage. And any opportunity I had I would just go hiking and camping. But never killed a bear, never killed an animal or anything like that. It's just not in my makeup.
And how did
Speaker 29: you deal with the harsh winters? Because...
Speaker 29: in Anchorage in particular, you know, that can get
a
Speaker 30: little difficult to deal with, right?
- More
Speaker 24 (lower-pitched voice): than that, you know, I
Speaker 8 (lower-pitched voice): worked, I concentrated on real estate because that was a way to get my name out there. But I also worked one winter on the Alaska Railroad
as a
Speaker 8 (lower-pitched voice): brakeman, I might say. And then when I had a development called the Alaska Village, trailers would move
in,
Speaker 8 (lower-pitched voice): And I would have to hook them up and sometimes 40 degrees below zero out there. You work for about 20 minutes, get in, warm up, then go back out and do another 20 minutes of work and so I've
Man 7: experienced, in fact the coldest I've ever been was on a campaign trip to Delta, Alaska
Speaker 8 (lower-pitched voice): where we stayed in a motel and in the motel,
Speaker 8 (lower-pitched voice): You know, it was the top heat and dressed, and the temperature was 62 degrees. That's cold.
And where is
Speaker 31: that in Alaska? In Delta, Alaska. Where regionally is that?
That's in
Speaker 31: the middle of Alaska.
Speaker 32: Okay.
That's in
Speaker 26 (lower-pitched voice): the north of Fairbanks, northeast of Fairbanks. So in the
Speaker 33: tundra?
Well,
Speaker 33: it's all tundra. Right. Well,
not
Speaker 34: Juno, actually, where I was. It's not tundra.
Man 7: Juno in southeast is fjord country. That's why it's so beautiful. When you get up to, when you go beyond
Speaker 26 (lower-pitched voice): Yakutat, you're up into Prince William Sound, you get a different kind of beauty.
Speaker 26 (lower-pitched voice): And then you go north of that, up in Mt. McKinley in that area. In the Alaska Range, that's a different kind of beauty. Then you get the Brooks Range, that's another range that's up within the Arctic Circle. And that's another kind of beauty. And then of course you got the Deep Arctic, which is really
Man 7: beautiful in its starkness. Not darkness, starkness.
Man 7: So, I've always was blessed that I would have to
Speaker 26 (lower-pitched voice): campaign around the state and do nothing more than in the process of enjoying the beauty of Alaska.
I
Speaker 8 (lower-pitched voice): miss it now, but of course at my age, the winters get longer and colder even though there's environment, climate warming in Alaska,
Man 7: but it's still, every so often I'll
compare
Man 7: On my iPhone,
Speaker 8 (lower-pitched voice): the temperatures in Anchorage and where I'm living now in California, the seaside, and the temperatures in other parts of the country. So, where I live now, it doesn't get too cold and it doesn't get too warm, and it's always, by and large, sweater weather. Right.
Speaker 1 (lower-pitched voice): So, you were defeated in a primary election in 1980. Right.
What
Speaker 1 (lower-pitched voice): were the circumstances which led up to that, to you having faced primary challengers, and what was that race like?
Well, it's
Speaker 26 (lower-pitched voice): like anything else. When you lose, there's a certain attitude or you feel defeated. But what was going on in my mind at the time is
I was
Speaker 8 (lower-pitched voice): advocating –
Speaker 8 (lower-pitched voice): an economic approach that was somewhat
Man 7: complex and so I devoted half of the money I raised to pushing for the enactment of the
Speaker 8 (lower-pitched voice): AGSOC, the Alaska General Stock Ownership Corporation, which of course is a process that could be used nationally to alter the bad effects
of
Man 7: capitalism. And so what happened is I was, most of the accomplishments that I had as a senator were always, were in my first term. And that's unique to most members of Congress. And
the second term I was,
Man 7: not as successful in getting things done that I thought were important. And slowly I took on issues that alienated the basic constituencies
Speaker 8 (lower-pitched voice): of
mine. The
Speaker 8 (lower-pitched voice): fishing community and the smaller communities of Alaska were angry with me because I was a supporter of the law of the sea. The Native community was angry with me because I wouldn't support
Speaker 8 (lower-pitched voice): the Alaska lands deal, which Stevens and others had organized, whereby the environmental community was able to lock up excessively Alaska, and so by the time
I was
Man 7: writing for re-election, my heart wasn't in it, but I had no place to go. I didn't get into
the
Man 7: Senate with any substantial wealth and I didn't come out with any. So I really didn't have a place to go, but my thought was if I got re-elected then I would concentrate on the Alaska, the AGSOC, the Alaska Stock Warnership Corporation.
Man 7: which was buying a piece of
Speaker 8 (lower-pitched voice): the Alaska pipeline, and they would throw off three or four hundred dollars a year to every single citizen of the state, based upon their ownership of this capital
Man 7: emplacement, which was, of course, the pipeline. So, after I left office for about
Speaker 8 (lower-pitched voice): ten years, never got involved in politics, never made any speeches.
a
Speaker 26 (lower-pitched voice): group essentially wanted me to run for governor. I just didn't want to have anything to do with politics. And so what had happened about 10 years out, after being a
Speaker 8 (lower-pitched voice): consultant here and there, not very successful because my heart wasn't into making money or nor my intellect, but it just dawned on me because I had been grappling with this problem, how to solve the problems, the shortcomings
Speaker 26 (lower-pitched voice): of representative government.
And
Speaker 26 (lower-pitched voice): so it dawned on me about 10 years after, which would be about 1989, 90, and it just hit me, the answers to people. You know, there's only two venues for a real change, and that's the government, which chooses not to do it because that would disrupt the
Man 7: control by the elites and the people who do
Man 7: under the Constitution defined powers to be able to enact laws. The law
Speaker 26 (lower-pitched voice): making, which is the core of human society, the core of human governance is held by a monopoly of representative government. What we do is on election day we give our legislative power, our sovereign power to representatives
Speaker 26 (lower-pitched voice): And then they hold it as a monopoly, they're the only ones that can make laws at the federal level. And so, all we can do is protest, bang, write letters, hope that these elected officials will do the right thing. But when in point of fact, these elected officials are financed by the forces of Wall Street, the military-industrial complex. And first and foremost, their position is to protect the status
quo.
Speaker 26 (lower-pitched voice): And if they got an extra amount of time, maybe help the people to some degree. That's where we're at today. And that's the reason why the name of the book that I'm working on is called Human Governance, The Failure of Representative Government and a Solution, the People. So
in
Speaker 1 (lower-pitched voice): the very first debate in
Speaker 5 (lower-pitched voice): the 2008 primary cycle, there's a clip that you can still find on YouTube, obviously, where you're discussing the Iraq War.
And
Speaker 5 (lower-pitched voice): the moderator
Speaker 1 (lower-pitched voice): Brian Williams asked you to name candidates on stage who you feel have done a particularly poor job in combating the Bush administration's approach to that war. And at one point, Joe Biden raises his hand and waves at you and you respond saying, quote, you have a certain arrogance to him. Because at the time, Biden was promoting this plan where he wanted the U.S. to impose a partition plan.
On
Speaker 1 (lower-pitched voice): Iraq. And your point was that it took a certain amount of arrogance to presume that the U.S. could tell Iraqis how they should govern themselves after having invaded their country and, you know, destroying it. That's
Speaker 8 (lower-pitched voice): accurate. And of course, you want to carry that forward because Joe's leadership of the Judiciary Committee during the Anita Hill…
Speaker 8 (lower-pitched voice): was
Man 7: equally arrogant. It was arrogant on his part to make the decision that when you had two other witnesses that would corroborate Anita Hill, and he chose not
Speaker 10 (lower-pitched voice): to call them. And he chose also to unleash and let our inspector savage like a terrible prosecutor, Anita Hill. Well, that's arrogance. Now, and it goes with power.
Speaker 10 (lower-pitched voice): People that have power for a
Man 7: long time develop a certain arrogance. That's the reason why our judiciary situation is really such a mess. Because these judges are
Speaker 10 (lower-pitched voice): appointed, not elected, appointed for life. That means that, you know, you can talk about corruption which is putting your hand out and getting a bribe.
Speaker 10 (lower-pitched voice): But the intellectual corruption,
Man 7: many times, is much more serious and much more debilitating to the processes of governance that we see by, if power corrupts, it corrupts absolutely everybody. And so if power corrupts, obviously our judiciary system is rampant with this kind
Speaker 38: of arrogant corruption.
But what
Speaker 29: about the arrogance in
Speaker 20 (lower-pitched voice): particular that he displayed when he was touting at
the time
Speaker 20 (lower-pitched voice): his plan to partition Iraq?
Well,
Speaker 10 (lower-pitched voice): here again, that's part of foreign policy. First off, he voted for the war, which was ridiculous. This was probably the worst foreign policy
Man 7: mistake in all of American history. And so after voting, it takes a certain amount of arrogance of the people who voted for the
Man 7: To think that you can go into another country, do away with their leadership and think you've solved the problem. And then when you've realized that you've lied to get into that position, then what you say, "Oh, we're there to establish democracy." This is a little bit like the naivete of Woodrow Wilson in setting us off on a trajectory of unlimited wars.
Man 7: when he made the statement that our entry into the first world war was an effort to make the world safe for democracy. These are platitudes that mean nothing. What you have to measure is what these actions that are done by arrogant people holding power, you measure that loss of life.
And like what
Man 7: we're doing in Venezuela or what we've done in other countries, you know, under Clinton we, what, had 500,000 children die and the Secretary of State, Matt Albright, said, "Well, that was collateral damage." That's murder. And you know, you heard the cliché is, you
Speaker 10 (lower-pitched voice): know, kill one person and you're a murderer. Kill a million and you have a foreign
policy.
Speaker 39: Right. Go ahead. No,
Speaker 40: that's OK. I just I just spent my bullet there. OK.
Speaker 4: Voters
have
Speaker 5 (lower-pitched voice): been asked recently to describe why it is that they're supporting Biden. And often what you'll
hear is
Speaker 1 (lower-pitched voice): them saying something to the effect of, well, the overwhelming priority right now has
to be
Speaker 1 (lower-pitched voice): to defeat Trump. So we don't want to get too involved in the policy disputes within the Democratic Party. Everything has to be toward defeating Trump.
Speaker 1 (lower-pitched voice): And even some of Biden's early endorsers in the Congress, particularly in the Congressional Black Caucus, where a few powerful members have endorsed Biden already, their logic is similar to where they're saying Biden is best equipped to defeat Trump. He's the most, quote unquote, electable.
Speaker 2 (lower-pitched voice): How do you respond to that kind of rationale? Well,
first
Speaker 8 (lower-pitched voice): off, he's not the most electable nationally. He's never been successful in that regard.
Speaker 8 (lower-pitched voice): Secondly, they're making a compromise that
Man 7: need not be made, there's a time to compromise. That's if you can't get anything better. We can get better. Well, I think the Democratic Party right now, which is so obsessed with the President Trump,
When
Man 7: you have to just accept the fact that Trump is a narcissistic fool, and he holds the power of any more power than any other individual in the world holds, but recognize that if you look closely at Trump, and there's been a psychiatrist who has really defined
Man 7: Trump's trajectory where right now he's getting more losing mental acuity and he will, in the next 18 months, Trump will lose the presidency. We don't have to worry about making all kinds of compromises with reality and with what's possible because Trump is imploding.
Man 7: and it'll get worse, and so if somebody were to engage him in a debate, you know, these other Republicans that he beat the last time, that was one style that he used. That style is no longer operable. Fine. It will sustain his base, but you're talking about 25-27% of the electorate, which are dumb as fence posts.
And
Man 7: so we don't have to worry about that. What we have to worry about as Democrats is not to do foolish things. And what I considered foolish was the minute he was elected, everybody called, not everybody, a large number of Democratic leaders and fundraisers calling for his immediate impeachment. There was nothing to impeach him on at that point in time. And right now, the
Speaker 10 (lower-pitched voice): impeachment would go nowhere. It would just suck up the oxygen when the people want us to accomplish things. And so what the Democrats ought to focus on
Speaker 10 (lower-pitched voice): is passing the best legislative package it can and sending it over to the Senate and watch it languish in no activity at all. And this will set us up to the same thing that Harry Truman had with the do-nothing Congress that got him re-elected. So we don't have to go after Trump. What we have to do is get the progressive legislation that's so important to benefit our citizens, get that passed, sent over to the Senate,
Speaker 10 (lower-pitched voice): And let the people look at the Senate in its stupidity and its ignorance. But then at the same time, just let Trump get all the visibility
Man 7: that you need. And in this visibility, he will make a fool of himself, which is really what he is down deep.
And
Man 7: so his diminished abilities, his diminished mental abilities are eroding away from him. And that's what the psychiatrist was observing with respect to the way he slurs, the fact that he can't read anymore, and he's really always taking an issue and dumbing it down
Man 7: whatever crosses his mind. There's dangers in that, and we have no control over that. Because the like of Pompeo and Bolton, you know, they can play him like a fiddle. In fact, somebody wrote an article, the title of that, that Bolton's playing the president just like a fiddle, and we'll get him into a war. And I don't think that he's interested in going to war. He's more interested in the ego,
Man 7: visibility, which is of course, which is what he did with Kim and what he wants to do with Iran is have them talk so he can get these photo opportunities with "our enemies", who are not really our enemies. So, the Democrats should just concentrate on legislation and they do have a responsibility of oversight.
And
Man 7: so I think that the various committees that are looking into getting information about Trump's personal economic activities, his misuse of power, is trying to overcome judicial actions, it's fine, investigate that, but make that, but unfortunately the
media
Man 7: going to focus on that as opposed to focusing on the need that AOC and Bernie have articulating with respect to doing something about the Green New Deal.
Speaker 41: Now that's got some attention but it but that's the that's what's important.
Right. Gerald
Speaker 42: Nadler who's
Speaker 1 (lower-pitched voice): the chairman of the House Judiciary Committee was overheard making a statement of some kind
Speaker 1 (lower-pitched voice): That his intention, you know, roughly speaking, was, like you said, to endorse or to impeach rather Trump just
after he
Speaker 1 (lower-pitched voice): was elected. And that also plays into why Democrats started immediately proclaiming that Trump was a pawn of Russia or a compromise by Russia somehow. And not only could there be political disadvantages to that, as you laid out, it
also has
Speaker 1 (lower-pitched voice): had the effect, I think, of ratcheting up tensions with a nuclear armed power.
Speaker 43: to the point that we're in a we're in a very precarious situation in that respect
well
Speaker 10 (lower-pitched voice): there's no question about that and that's one of the flaws now i'm not familiar with nadler's initial comment in that regard but i'll point out that you don't need a comment by network or the republicans to realize
Speaker 8 (lower-pitched voice): that and this
Speaker 10 (lower-pitched voice): started in obama's administration
Speaker 10 (lower-pitched voice): that the Department of Defense has been authorized to $1.7 trillion, mind you, to refurbish our nuclear arsenal. Now, when you look at the record of cost overruns with the military, you appreciate that $1.7 trillion is really
three plus
Speaker 10 (lower-pitched voice): trillion dollars that
Man 7: we're going to spend on nuclear refurbishment when, in point of fact, these nuclear weapons are not usable. Anybody who were to unleash 20 or 100 nuclear devices would trigger the planet into a nuclear winter and we're all going to
die.
Man 7: That's what's
Speaker 10 (lower-pitched voice): going on, and the Defense Department has said this is our number
Man 7: one priority, is to refurbish our nuclear capability. And like I say, with three trillion dollars
you can
Man 7: take care of education, you can take care of the single payer healthcare, you can take care of a whole
Speaker 10 (lower-pitched voice): host of needs that are required, but
no.
Speaker 10 (lower-pitched voice): This is the Republicans to a man voting for this. And also, you don't hear any Democrats, candidates, members of Congress talking about this. This is the heart of the military industrial complex that Tulsi Gabbard and Bernie are talking about. And so, we're trillion dollars on a weapon that in point of fact can't be used
Speaker 44: because it's a suicidal
weapon.
Could you
Speaker 45: envision a scenario where you do choose to endorse one of the candidates, whether it's Tulsi or Bernie, if you feel
Speaker 46: that they most adequately represent the issues that are dearest to you?
Well,
Speaker 10 (lower-pitched voice): there's no question about that. Now,
Speaker 8 (lower-pitched voice): I've made a statement via the kids who run my campaign that I'm running to win.
I
Speaker 8 (lower-pitched voice): think I have a little more humility than many of the other candidates because I think the likelihood of my winning even though I'm trying to win
Man 7: is not very, very high. And so if that being the case, if that becomes evident
as a
Man 7: result of more accurate polling and presently polling is not accurate as to what's going
on,
And
Man 7: not that the technology is not accurate, it's just that it's just too early to be able to let things filter out.
Speaker 8 (lower-pitched voice): And so once that's done, there's no question that I would endorse Hillary and Tulsi and Warren.
Speaker 47 (lower-pitched voice): Bernie and Tulsi, not Hillary. What did
Speaker 8 (lower-pitched voice): I say?
You
Speaker 48: said Hillary, which is the polar opposite of what you meant.
Speaker 8 (lower-pitched voice): No, it's Bernie, Tulsi, and Warren where I would concentrate my.
Speaker 8 (lower-pitched voice): my endorsement and efforts, and efforts because I'm in it as long as I'm healthy and I think that I've got maybe five more good years
Man 7: of health that I would just work my heart out. Now, the best way to do that is with the publication of my book.
Man 7: Which actually takes the agenda put forth by the people that I would support, takes that agenda and puts it before the American people and gives them the tools to enact that agenda. And that, of course, would be the most destabilizing thing that could ever be done to bring to heel the elites that control our society.
So
Speaker 49: in
Speaker 5 (lower-pitched voice): 2013, I was fascinated because you took part in what was called the Citizen
Speaker 1 (lower-pitched voice): Hearing on Disclosure, which dealt with unidentified flying objects and that sort of thing. And it was sort of laughed off because the instinctive reaction on the part of much of the media is to dismiss any
Speaker 50: discussion of that as kooky.
But
Speaker 51: sure enough, a couple of years later in 2017, the New York Times broke a story
where
Speaker 51: apparently the Pentagon had a secret program
Speaker 29: where they did investigate UFOs, and apparently this was done at the behest of Harry Reid, who represented
Speaker 2 (lower-pitched voice): Nevada, obviously, where there is maybe a disproportionate attention to this issue. So I'm wondering how you reflect on that,
Speaker 52: and what was your reaction to that revelation when it came out?
Well,
Speaker 8 (lower-pitched voice): first off, the hearings that were set
up
one
Speaker 8 (lower-pitched voice): week long with several former members of Congress listening to the testimony was just awesome. I was extremely
Man 7: impressed. Now I came at the issue because I don't have any great expertise, so I don't have the time to really dig in to the issue. But I came at it very simply with a view that I think it would be the height of human arrogance.
to
Man 7: think that there's not other sentient beings out in the cosmos. We're just beginning to make sense and knowledge of the cosmos, just all the attention of the black hole. Here again, if you look at the cosmos and you say, "Boy, look at
us."
There's
Man 7: got to be something else out there beyond us. We can't be the only ones. So that's where I come at the subject. I don't focus my attention on a great deal of study over that. You know, here again, we each have only so much time and I have focused my attention
on
Man 7: solving the problems of human governance and that's what this book that I hope to finish here shortly will make a contribution in that regard. I never felt until the kids came along asking me to run that I would live to see the possibility of direct democracy.
Man 7: But as a result of the visibility that I was able to get thanks to the campaign initiated by the young guys that are running my campaign, that this visibility gives me an opportunity now to put this manual of how we're going to bring about the legislature of the people, to put that manual out there so people can see it. Now we have thousands and millions of people
who have
Man 7: passed through and focused on my candidacy or the issues that I promulgate. Now, once the book is out there, then the manual, and I was putting it out hoping that somebody in a number of years might focus on it and say after another terrible tragedy and say, "Well, this is the answer. We have to find a way to make people empowered to make laws."
Man 7: And the manual that I talk about doesn't only apply it to the United States, it can be done in any country. In fact, I would hope that it would be done in the majority of OECD countries. And as a result of that, we could then reorganize the United Nations and bring about a world federation, which is the only way we're ever
Speaker 53: going to see peace on this planet.
Speaker 54: And how did you react to the revelation
Speaker 5 (lower-pitched voice): in 2017 that the Defense Department did in fact have a program to analyze you know, aerial activity that was of unknown providence so they actually were taking this issue seriously and Harry Reid was involved in getting this program
funded.
Man 7: Well, I reacted to it, same old, same old. In other words, we are beset in this country with an unbelievable amount of secrecy.
Man 7: And it does not serve us well because if you really want to be a healthy functioning democracy, the people have to know exactly what their government is doing in their name and that way they can weigh in. But we don't even have anything close to that because everything is and it's a natural for people in power to want secrecy to protect what they do wrong.
Man 7: Because then they'll advertise what they do right, but the secrecy will protect them in that regard. And so, and that's what would happen if the people are able to make laws in a deliberative, now I'm talking about a very deliberative fashion, then they will be able to put aside the secrecy to know what's going on. The recent article by Chelsea Manning about talking about a book that she's working on,
Man 7: You know, she doesn't want to write about her trial and what happened to her in captivity and the torturing and all. She doesn't want to write about that because most of that is considered confidential and secret.
Man 7: Well, why the hell shouldn't we know about what happens in our prisons? Why does that have to—our military prisons—why does that have to be secret? Why do we have to have secrecy surrounding Guantanamo Bay? You know, this is ridiculous. Let me give you an example of secrecy.
Man 7: We have a troika, a triad of nuclear when we talk about refurbishing our nuclear establishment. We have the establishment which is a triad. That is that back in the 50s, in order to duplicate admirals and generals, we gave a piece of the nuclear pie to the army, a piece to the navy, and a piece to the air force. Well, we now say that the reason why we need the triad,
that if our enemy,
Man 7: were to launch an attack and knock out one of the elements of the triad, the other two elements would be available to retaliate. Truth of the matter is, if anybody were to attack us in a serious fashion at the nuclear level,
then of
Man 7: course they'll trigger, we don't need to retaliate, we're going to die anyway. Because they'll trigger a nuclear winter. Now, what we could do, as a matter of foreign policy,
and
Man 7: it would be very meaningful, and that is to do away with the Army Triad, do away with the Air Force Triad, and we still have
the Navy
Man 7: element of the Triad, where we have 12 Trident submarines, each one has 280 nuclear warheads.
Man 7: Now, if you can imagine, 280, that can hold a world hostage. So we would be more than secure with one leg of the triad. And I would not do away with these two other legs in negotiation with another nuclear power. No, we should just do it. It doesn't threaten our security. We should just do it, but we would then prove to the world that we're serious about bringing the nuclear capability worldwide down to zero.
Man 7: Now, that would mean, and then of course what we could do is we'd have some legitimacy to then call, have to ask the UN to call forth a conference made up of the eight nuclear powers plus Japan and Germany and India and Indonesia. And then we could have a meaningful negotiations to do away with the nuclear capability.
Man 7: And who would join that? Kim Jong-un would join it just with the others, and Israel too. You know, they don't own up to the fact that they've got nukes, but we would invite them to a conference. And that kind of a conference where we have really demonstrated our bona fides by doing away with two legs and not doing away with these two legs of the triad on a quid pro quo with other nuclear powers, just demonstrate. And there's no risk to it.
Man 7: I'm reminded of McNamara being questioned at the end of his tour as the Secretary of Defense. Somebody asked him, "Well, how much could we really cut the defense budget without threatening our security?" He said 50%.
And
Man 7: McNamara is probably one of the brightest persons we had at the head of the Defense Department. So no, these are the directions we need to go, and these are the directions that are basically not addressed by the
Speaker 47 (lower-pitched voice): plethora of candidates we have running for president.
One
Speaker 29: last question, and it actually relates to your broader point about direct democracy. I don't know if you saw this, but just last
week
Speaker 29: these citizens of Denver successfully passed a referendum to decriminalize psilocybin mushrooms, which in the past has kind of been discounted as something that only hippies are concerned with, but actually there have been a lot of rigorous scientific studies demonstrating that consumption of this substance can alleviate depression, people
with
Speaker 29: severe illnesses have taken them and has, you know, reduced their mental stress and trauma. And I know that you've been vocal about declaring that the war on drugs
Speaker 20 (lower-pitched voice): has been a failure. I'm just wondering what your response to that, you know, somewhat groundbreaking initiative was, if you happen to see it.
Yeah, it was
Speaker 8 (lower-pitched voice): a referendum, not an initiative, but
Speaker 8 (lower-pitched voice): The initiative, I used to call what I now call the Legislature of the People, the Citizens Initiative, National Citizens Initiative. Most people aren't very familiar with the initiative
Man 7: process, and so therefore the terminology, it's easier for people to understand, is you're going to be part of, as a lawmaker, of the Legislature of the People, and this can be, this is all laid out.
Man 7: From the people's point of view, they don't realize that they do a lot of lawmaking. Whenever a school board puts forth bonds to build schools or to build infrastructure,
Man 7: the entity in question, and the people vote on that, they're voting to encumber themselves with this death. Well, that's lawmaking at its finest and most extensive. So there's no miracle in, or it's, you know, talking about the people being able to make laws. Now, referendum is different, Brexit is a classic example of that.
Man 7: where you had Cameron, Prime Minister Cameron kicked the can down the road and had a referendum
Speaker 10 (lower-pitched voice): on whether or not to stay in the EU. Now, the tragedy there was that that was terrible law making.
Speaker 10 (lower-pitched voice): because the people were not informed. When I talk about lawmaking, I'm talking about deliberative lawmaking, where you have a process where the people can become knowledgeable and educated about the intricacies of the issue they're about to vote
on. And
Speaker 10 (lower-pitched voice): so that's not what happened in Britain. And so now you see this whole brouhaha over Brexit, when the only answer was by the
Man 7: comedian,
Man 7: who pointed out that the answer is to declare that referendum void because the people weren't given the information about the consequences. And so, but no, the politicians are so steeped in their stupidity and digging a hole, it's just beyond, and so this will not only damage Brexit, it will not only damage Britain,
it
Speaker 10 (lower-pitched voice): will damage Europe and damage parts.
Speaker 10 (lower-pitched voice): and the rest of the world. So no, you've
Man 7: got to be very careful when you're talking about and no, I applauded what took place in Colorado in this regard and what took place in a number of states using the initiative to get the acceptance of cannabis or marijuana.
Man 7: How tragic is it that here you have a plant that's been known from the middle ages to have some very beneficial properties and of course it can be psychedelic too, but why deny the ability to research it and to tease out what these properties are that are so beneficial to human beings? We have not done any of that to speak of.
Man 7: And I hoped that we would overcome the ridiculous position held in the United States that we have to have a war on drugs. What we ought to do is decriminalize all drugs and follow the pattern of Portugal.
in
Man 7: letting people who have drug problems
Speaker 47 (lower-pitched voice): be treated as a public health issue rather than a criminal issue in that regard.
And
Speaker 5 (lower-pitched voice): are you familiar at all with the substance of what was approved in Denver last week by a referendum, this particular drug,
Speaker 55: which is seen to have a lot of potential in curing a lot of psychological maladies? Very
Speaker 10 (lower-pitched voice): much so. I read the article in the paper about
it.
And
Speaker 10 (lower-pitched voice): something that
Man 7: came across my computer screen. And so I'm just very happy. Whenever you see some advances in this area of human governance, it makes me extremely happy. What I'm trying to do by creating a legislature of the people is to accelerate that process. Because the people, when you look at the people...
You
Man 7: have a choice right now, you can be governed by a minority or you can be governed by a majority. The majority are the people and so that's the reason why I feel so deeply about the work that I've been doing for the last 25, 30 years. This legislation, this manual that I've written about creating a legislature of the people didn't jump on the table, it had to be discussed,
vetted,
Man 7: And it was written over a 25-year period. And so what you'll see next summer in this regard is going to be the product of all that effort. And here too, once the people are empowered in a deliberative way of making laws, you'll see such a change in the governance of our society.
And
Man 7: if we can do it in the United States, we'll race around the world like wildfire. Until we find a way to organize the world as we move into a cyber society, we're going to be in deep trouble more than we've ever seen in the
Speaker 26 (lower-pitched voice): past.
Well, I want to
Speaker 5 (lower-pitched voice): thank you for spending an extended period of time with me. I'm actually curious, since you launched your campaign, you've done a number of podcasts.
Speaker 5 (lower-pitched voice): which are more uninhibited than typical media and allow people to actually express their thoughts at full, you know, at a full volume. What is, what has, what has been your experience
Speaker 56: doing these podcasts? How do you, how do you
Speaker 57: perceive it?
Speaker 56: Well,
Man 7: it's, it's, it's an opportunity to speak out on issues and give warning and all of that. And so I,
Man 7: Here again, I feel I have a certain messianic drive in this regard, and so getting these podcasts, getting these interviews, gives me an opportunity to get a message, and the message that I'm trying to get across is very difficult, and that is that the answers with the people…
with
Man 7: deliberative democracy, the answer is not with our leaders. And so when I look at the presidential candidates running for office, I winnow it down to those who have a decent agenda. But will they be able to get that agenda
enacted?
Man 7: Maybe in a small portion of it, regardless of who's elected president, a small portion of it will get enacted, but all of it could be enacted if you empowered the people to make laws. And we have to find a way to break, and I think I have with this manual, break the monopoly that representatives have on lawmaking and a monopoly
Speaker 38: that sustains the 1%, the elites, to control our society.
Speaker 59: Okay.
Speaker 5 (lower-pitched voice): And on a practical level, according to the dictates of the DNC, candidates need 65,000 unique donors as one of the criteria to be able to enter the debates. How are you doing on that front? Do you anticipate that you're going
Speaker 45: to actually gain entry into the debates?
Speaker 24 (lower-pitched voice): Well, all I can do is ask my campaign leaders.
Speaker 26 (lower-pitched voice): David Oak and Henry Williams and others to what's the status and David told me that we're at 35,000
Man 7: voters at this point in time and we have what raised maybe close to $80,000 and they're using the money to now advertise to try to get more people to vote in this regard. So will we make it? I don't know, but even if we don't make it,
Man 7: we'll continue a campaign of information that will sort of invade on a segue kind of way into the campaign that's going forward within the Democratic Party. Now, I've given up on the Republican Party, and the statements made
by
Man 7: presidential campaign, or they're going to cooperate with the Republicans. The Republicans have been on a suicidal mission to destroy the Constitution, and they've succeeded to a good degree. But we don't need to compromise with them, we need to take this agenda we know to be correct and put it before the people and let them make a final decision
on it. Right.
Speaker 5 (lower-pitched voice): Okay, well, maybe after listening to our discussion,
Speaker 2 (lower-pitched voice): there will
be some
who are
Speaker 2 (lower-pitched voice): encouraged to donate and to increase your total, so maybe you have a better opportunity to enter the debates. So that's a potential function of these types of conversations. So I just want to thank you again for taking the time.
Well,
Man 7: thank you for having me on and letting me go on and talk about these problems. All right.
Speaker 38: Senator Gravel, thanks again. Thank you. Bye. Thank you very much. Bye.
Thank you.
All
Speaker 60: right. There you have it. I hope you found it edifying. I sure did. Please remember to
Speaker 1 (lower-pitched voice): subscribe on Patreon. You can support financially through PayPal. You can subscribe to the podcast on iTunes and Stitcher. And also please subscribe on YouTube where I post additional non-podcast material. All right. See you soon.